there is a concept of data rays that
plays an important role in considering
how we can relax consistency a data race
occurs when there is a data dependence
between axises that are on different
cores and these axises are not ordered
by synchronization so for a data race to
occur we need to really have one
processor reading another writing to the
same variable or the other way around or
both of them
writing and the axises on these
different cores are not ordered by
synchronization so here's an example of
a data race a data race here exists
because really we can have this happen
or in another execution this store might
occur before the load and thus this can
happen too so this is a data RM in
contrast something like this where we do
low a then a barrier and this thread
participates in that barrier and then
does store a
there is a data dependence between
axises but they're clearly ordered by
synchronization this one will happen
before this one because of the barrier
synchronization so there is no data race
here conceptually a data race allows any
order of these operations and that might
change the outcome of the program
whereas
here we know what's going to happen then
there is a concept of a data Ras free
program which which is a program that
cannot create any data races in its
execution pretty much that program is
considered to be well synchronized so
that any accesses to data are correctly
ordered by synchronization barriers
locks Flags Etc a key property of data
Race Free programs is that they behave
exactly the same as they would in
sequential consistency even if we run
them in any relaxed consistency model
why is that so well because if your
synchronization is implemented correctly
then your synchronization is going to
create the right orderings for things
and then there is no
opportunity for the reorderings that
might violate sequential consistency so
a data race free program is actually
sequentially consistent even if we run
it on a machine that doesn't support
sequential consistency as long as
synchronization is correctly implemented
for that machine but keep in mind that
while you're debugging your programs
even if you intend them to be data Race
Free they may not actually be data race
free in which case
theoretically anything can happen so
pretty much while we are debugging a
program to remove data races the
behavior of that program on a weekly
consistent system might be very weird
and thus it makes debugging really
really difficult so for most programs
that are correct and that means data
Race Free we can relax the consistency
model but for debugging it really helps
if we can support sequential
consistency so some processors actually
have support to flip between sequential
consistency or some more relaxed
consistency that gives us better
performance so that when you're
debugging you can use sequential
consistency until you're reasonably sure
that your program is working correctly
and is data Ras free at which point we
can run it on a weaker consistency model
to benefit from the additional
reordering that the processor is now
allowed to do